Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is officially מ"ט, Mem-Tet,
but we are a bit behind. We start at the משנה Mishnah
at the bottom of מ"ח עמוד א'. Mem-Chet Amud Aleph. We've been
dealing with the father's rights over the daughter and then transitioning to
the husband's rights and parallel responsibilities to his wife, and we have
already now yesterday framed the basic dimensions of the כתובה Kesuvah and
its obligations. And now we turn to the משנה Mishnah at the
bottom of מ"ח עמוד א', Mem-Chet Amud Aleph, which gets us also
to the relationship of the father to the husband and the transition
of the daughter from the father's house to the husband's house. As
I've been saying for the last few days, in this מסכת, Masechet,
it sounds very much like the תורה Torah that the woman is
never independent. She goes from the father's house to the husband's house,
one man sort of controlling and being responsible for her to another.
In the חז"ל, Chazal, they understand that once she hits בוגרת, Bogeret,
puberty, she becomes independent, but you don't see that here. Here it's
just that straight transition. And within this is the discussion of exactly,
if you would, the core of our מסכת, Masechet, which is the
כתובה Kesuvah and its obligations, the wedding, the obligations at the time
that the marriage is real, goes from קידושין Kiddushin to נישואין, Nisuin,
and also what that moment is. What is that moment of נישואין?
Nisuin? How do you identify it? We call it חופה. Chuppah. What
exactly is that moment where that changes? Because even after betrothal, even
after קידושין, Kiddushin, she is still in her father's control and her
father's house, even though technically she's a married woman. The actual change,
going to the חתן's Chosson house, comes at the time of נישואין.
Nisuin. So let's see how we exactly identify that. So the משנה
Mishnah starts at the bottom of מ"ח עמוד א'. Mem-Chet Amud Aleph.
לעולם היא ברשות האב עד שתיכנס לרשות הבעל לנישואין.
Le'olam hi b'reshut ha'av ad
shetikanes l'reshut haba'al l'nisuin. She is always, presumably even after betrothal, in
the father's control until she enters into the husband's control for the
purposes of נישואין, Nisuin, which is very nice and abstract but doesn't
exactly tell us what that moment is. Some apparently had the גרסא
Gersa here, לרשות הבעל לחופה. l'reshut haba'al l'chuppah. The גמרא Gemara certainly
has a ברייתא Braita later that effectively says חופה, Chuppah, but this
remains our גרסא Gersa of this משנה Mishnah is more abstract. Even
חופה Chuppah we don't know what it is. We will see in
the גמרא. Gemara. Now, מסר האב לשלוחי הבעל. Masar ha'av lishluchei haba'al.
Now, by the way, you really again see this vision of her
as an object. She is a thing that's being handed over. She's
going from one person's control, one man's control domain to another man's,
and now she's being handed over from one to the next like
so. She is handed, the father gave her over to the husband's
messengers. He sent אליעזר Eliezer there to go and collect her. Okay,
so הרי היא ברשות הבעל. Harei hi b'reshut haba'al. So even if
she hasn't yet gone to the husband's house, but she is being
transported there, accompanied there by the husband's messengers, that is seen as
being under the husband's control. הלך האב עם שלוחי הבעל. Halach ha'av
im shluchei haba'al.
Now let's say, however, that the husband accompanied, the father accompanied the
husband's messengers. או ששלחו שלוחי האב עם שלוחי הבעל, O sheshalchu shluchei
ha'av im shluchei haba'al, or he sent messengers to, his messengers to
accompany the husband's messengers. הרי היא ברשות האב. Harei hi b'reshut ha'av.
She still remains in the control of the father. So that would
be a little bit fit the language of the משנה, Mishnah, לעולם
היא ברשות האב. Le'olam hi b'reshut ha'av. If it's some yet some
middle state, then she has not yet entered into the husband's house
unless it's unambiguous now having crossed that line into the husband's control.
So if the father is accompanying and they're on their way to
the husband's house or the father's messengers, she's still under the father's
control, and it's not yet חופה, Chuppah, etc. מסרו שלוחי האב לשלוחי
הבעל הרי היא ברשות הבעל. Masru shluchei ha'av lishluchei haba'al harei hi
b'reshut haba'al. However,
if the husband's, father's messengers handed her over to the husband's messengers,
either they came to a point where they turned around and went
back, or they were bringing her to the husband's house, the father's
messengers, and then they bumped into the husband's messengers on their way
to pick her up, and they said, 'Here, why don't you take
her?' and they handed her off and then they turned around and
went home, then she is under the husband's control. Again, you see
very much this very much like this object that is being transported
concept here. Okay, but all of this emphasizes the idea of רשות.
Reshut. So if you had to ask yourself what is that moment
that is considered to be the moment of נישואין, Nisuin, I mean,
it doesn't even use the phrase חופה, Chuppah, you would have said
it was something about, you know, A, it's for the purpose of
נישואין. Nisuin. It's not just you're going and knocking on somebody's house
and visiting and dropping by. It's for the purpose of being a
wedded wife. But ultimately is somehow being in this idea of רשות,
Reshut, which starts presumably with going into his property, into his domain,
or to people that represent him and are somehow taking you under
his wing. But again, it's an interesting question, like what type of
sense is it to go with people, somebody's messenger? You're not yet
in the person's domain. You know, are they like doing the קניין
Kinyan for him? I mean, how much are we comparing this to
an actual act of acquisition? But somehow, you know, again, if one
imagines that this woman is not yet really an adult, 12, 12
and a half, under 12, then if you're going... Being transported, you're
sort of being controlled by and taken over by the husband's messengers.
But the exact moment is the exact sort of definition is not
clear though the idea of רשות reshus certainly dominates. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara.
מאי לעולם? Mai l'olam? What does it mean forever she's in the
father's control? What's that trying to emphasize? I'm just saying she's in
the father's control until the נישואין. nissuim. So מאי לעולם? mai l'olam?
לאפוקי ממשנה ראשונה. Lafokei mimishnah rishonah. To exclude the first משנה. Mishnah.
דתנן Ditnan we learned in a משנה: Mishnah: הגיע זמן ולא נישאו
אוכלות משלו ואוכלות בתרומה. higgia z'man velo nisu ocholos mishelo v'ocholos b'trumah.
You might remember that from the first דף. daf. Okay, if it's
the time for נישואין nissuim and it hasn't happened yet, the husband
is postponing or there's some other reasons why it's being delayed, then
his obligations of supporting her kicks in. He has to start supporting
her. Since they should have been married already by this time, and
she can even eat תרומה. trumah. If the husband's a כהן Kohen
and תרומה's trumah the easiest thing to support her with, it's less
expensive. She is technically considered his wife already for תרומה trumah purposes
already from the time of קידושין. kiddushin. Rabbinically we don't let that
happen yet until the time of נישואין. nissuim. But if they should
have had the נישואין nissuim and haven't had it and it's been
delayed, she can already eat תרומה. trumah. So therefore, that's what that
משנה Mishnah tells me. So I might have therefore thought, okay, so
then she can go to the husband's control while she's still in
the father's house. How does she go to the husband's control while
she's still in the father's house? She's in the father's house, there
hasn't been נישואין, nissuim, but the time for נישואין nissuim came and
she's considered to be in the husband's control that she eats תרומה.
trumah. Okay, everybody get how that's a middle—how she's still in the
father's house but somewhat under the husband's control that she eats תרומה?
trumah? So that was the משנה ראשונה. Mishnah Rishonah. So קא משמע
לן לעולם. kamashma lan l'olam. So that's why our משנה Mishnah said
לעולם l'olam to tell you that it's not true, we don't rule
that way, that we actually say that until she actually goes to
the husband's house she won't eat תרומה. trumah. Because we don't want
her eating תרומה trumah while she's in the father's house. לעולם, L'olam,
so even if the time for נישואין nissuim comes, she still remains
in the father's house and does not yet have a right to
eat תרומה.
trumah. How come in our משנה Mishnah one משנה Mishnah will contra—yeah,
מחלוקת machlokes within a משנה? Mishnah?
Well, that's a משנה ראשונה. Mishnah Rishonah. Later we're going to find
that the משנה Mishnah itself speaks about that that was an earlier
stage. So we already are aware that that's an earlier stage and
that this is a later stage. Exactly.
Okay. מסרה לשלוחי הבעל הרי היא ברשות
הבעל.
Masrah l'shluchei habaal harei
hi birshus habaal.
Fine.
So that's just—so that was just clarifying that we don't—we'll see that
more about that later, that even after the time of נישואין nissuim
she doesn't eat תרומה. trumah. Now we get to the exact moment
of transition. So what exactly and also whether it's all black and
white. So let's take a look. So אמר רב מסירתה לכל חוץ
מתרומה. amar Rav: mesirasah lakol chutz mitrumah. So since we just emphasized
תרומה, trumah, רב Rav says that this idea that she doesn't eat
תרומה trumah earlier, even true in this somewhat middle state of her
being on the way and going with the husband's messengers but not
yet having arrived at the husband's house. From our משנה Mishnah it
sounds like that by one hundred percent now she's considered a נשואה.
nesuah. But רב Rav says no, it's actually not true, that she
still doesn't eat תרומה trumah until she gets to—oh I will tell
you, until she gets to the husband's house. רב אסי אמר אף
לתרומה. Rav Assi amar: af l'trumah. And רב אסי Rav Assi says
no, the משנה Mishnah said she's completely under the husband's, that this
is the key moment giving over to the messengers of the husband.
So even for all purposes she's considered נשואה, nesuah, even for תרומה.
trumah. What's the issue? So there are two concerns for תרומה. trumah.
One concern for eating תרומה trumah earlier is that after נישואין, nissuim,
after the wedding night, the husband will decide, 'Oh, wait a minute,
I didn't realize, I see her now naked or whatever, something about
her I don't like, and therefore he decides the whole thing was
מקח טעות, mekach ta'us, wants to call the whole thing off, and
therefore it'll be somehow there'll be a basis for saying that it
was an invalid קידושין kiddushin which will be discovered at the wedding
night and then retroactively she would have eaten תרומה trumah without being
entitled to.' So that's why we want to wait until the moment
of נישואין. nissuim. Now you're right, technically you could say maybe even
after going to the husband's house until they've had sex. All right,
sorry, we got to draw the line somewhere. But certainly, רב Rav
is going to say until she's actually brought to the husband's house,
until they can actually be having sex, it's not going to be
the state yet where she can eat תרומה. trumah. That's one concern.
The other concern is, now that presumably explains רב. Rav. The position
of רב אסי Rav Assi is that no, the only reason she
doesn't eat תרומה trumah before the נישואין nissuim is because, exactly, you
send her תרומה, trumah, she's living in her father's house, she'll have
the rest of her family members eat and they're not allowed to
eat תרומה. trumah. So therefore as soon as she's out of her
father's house, even if she's not yet fully in the husband's house,
she can already eat תרומה, trumah, which by the way just points
us to the very obviously fascinating point that the גמרא Gemara is
picking up in this משנה, Mishnah, which is, it makes it seem
like there's absolutely no middle state. She leaves the father's house, enters
into the husband's house. But the גמרא Gemara actually imagines there is
some middle state. She's there carried by, being transported by the husband's
messengers, so she's clearly any control the father has has been abandoned.
He's not at the house, he's not there, the messengers are there.
She's fully out of the father's house. And she is being transported
to the husband's house and somewhat under the husband's control, but she's
not yet in the husband's house. There's she's not yet intimate with
the husband. They haven't yet had sex. So maybe this is an
interesting middle state. Left the father's house, somewhat under the husband's control,
but not fully in the husband's house. And is there something interesting
about this possible middle state that would not have all the laws
of being a married woman? And that's the question about תרומה. Terumah.
And the way רש״י Rashi understands this debate, the debate is what
is תרומה Terumah about? If תרומה's Terumah about being out of the
father's house, she can eat תרומה. Terumah. If תרומה Terumah is about
fully being with the husband, completely being with the husband, then she's
not yet entitled to eat תרומה. Terumah. Yes.
We've seen a couple places where they differentiate between יהודה Yehuda and
the rest of the place, so then shouldn't that be the case
for יהודה, Yehuda, right, because they do have...
All right, that's interesting, maybe. Yes. So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay. איתיבי רב הונא לרב אסי. Eiteivi Rav Huna le-Rav Assi. רב
הונא Rav Huna challenged רב אסי Rav Assi that says she's a
hundred percent in the husband's, you know, control or רשות. reshut. She's
a hundred percent נשואה nesuah even at this stage. ואמרי לה חיי
בר רב לרב אסי.
Ve-amri lah Chiya bar
Rav le-Rav Assi. And some say חיי בר רב Chiya bar Rav
asked רב אסי. Rav Assi.
It says לעולם היא ברשות האב עד שתיכנס לחופה. Le-olam hi bi-reshut
ha-av ad she-tikaneis la-chuppah. Apparently this was either a ברייתא Baraita or
their גירסא girsa of the משנה. Mishnah. She's always in the father's
control until she enters into the חופה. chuppah. So what does that
show? That shows that you need actually for there to be a
חופה, chuppah, that it's not just giving over to the husband's messengers.
Something is not complete, and חופה chuppah presumably literally means or symbolically
means in the husband's house. So being on the way is not
enough. There is some way that she's not fully נשואה nesuah in
this middle stage. So that was a challenge to רב אסי Rav
Assi who was רב׳ס Rav's בר פלוגתא. bar plugta. So interestingly, comes
רב Rav to defend
his, you know, his partner, his
interlocutor. Anyway, so אמר להו רב.
amar lehu Rav.
So רב Rav said to those that were asking the question on
רב אסי, Rav Assi, לאו אמינא לכו לא תחוזו בתר איפכא? lav
amina lacho lo techuzu batar ipcha? Haven't I told you don't look
for like contradictory thing, now opposite thing, not contradictory, meaning... what does
it mean it's opposite? So רש״י Rashi says that it means something
that could be interpreted in opposite ways. יכול לשנויי לכו. Yachol leshunayei
lacho. רב אסי Rav Assi could respond to you and say what
does that mean, until she goes to חופה? chuppah? מסירתה זו היא
כניסתה לחופה. Mesirata zo hi knissata la-chuppah. Until she goes to the
חופה chuppah means what's defined as חופה? chuppah? When she goes over
to the שלוחים shluchim of the בעל. baal. Why are you assuming
חופה chuppah means a later stage? The whole משנה Mishnah identified the
key moment was going over to the שלוחים shluchim of the בעל.
baal. He'll tell you that's what חופה chuppah means. Okay. So anyway,
we have this debate of רב Rav and רב אסי, Rav Assi,
that רב Rav says it's a middle step where she's left the
father's house but not yet a hundred percent in the husband's, and
the נפקא מינה nafka mina is תרומה. Terumah. ושמואל אמר, Ve-Shmuel amar,
לירושתה, leyerushata, that she
now, it's not exactly clear how much is included in that, but
שמואל Shmuel says once she's handed over to the שלוחים shluchim of
the בעל, baal, then he inherits her. If she were to die
now, he would inherit her. So שמואל Shmuel is saying that's the
only thing that she's considered in the control of the בעל, baal,
or is he saying, you know, everything except תרומה? Terumah? Right? You
know, on one hand you have שמואל Shmuel saying ירושה, yerusha, right,
and then you have, you know, here you've got the idea of
תרומה, Terumah, right, which maybe is going to require like חופה chuppah
or the בית הבעל beit ha-baal or something like that, right, because
then you have here the שלוחים, shluchim, you know, and you've got
here, right, the שלוחים shluchim are bringing her to the husband's house.
Okay, so שמואל Shmuel says well, if she were to die now
he would inherit her. Okay, what about all the other הלכות? halachot?
Can he annul her vows?
Does he have responsibility to feed her? Right? Is שמואל Shmuel saying
by ירושה yerusha he means everything but תרומה Terumah and he's really
saying the same as רב, Rav, or does he like just mean
ירושה? yerusha? Maybe most things are going to wait till she actually
comes to the husband's house. Not clear, right, about שמואל, Shmuel, but
he emphasizes just ירושה. yerusha. We'll see that echoed in a תוספתא
Tosefta coming up in the גמרא. Gemara.
So the discussion is about the nuance, the legal nuances of רשות,
reshut, like where do the responsibilities and the rights...
well the question is in this middle step where she is not
yet in the husband's house but being transported there and the משנה
Mishnah makes it sound like she's completely a נשואה, nesuah, is she
really a hundred percent a נשואה nesuah or is it some middle
step? So the גמרא Gemara says ריש לקיש אמר, Resh Lakish amar,
לכתובתה. lechtuvata.
So for the כתובה ketubah purposes. Now כתובה ketubah meaning what? As
you remember, כתובה, ketubah, one of the key things that the word
כתובה ketubah by itself means is the dowry. So the גמרא Gemara
says לכתובתה מאי היא? lechtuvata mai hi? What does לכתובתה lechtuvata mean?
דאי מתה ירת לה. de-i meta yarat lah. That if she were
to die he would inherit her. Inherit what? The dowry that she's
bringing in. Okay, that's the key aspect of ירושה. yerusha. What property
does she have? She has the dowry. So the גמרא Gemara says
היינו דשמואל. hainu de-Shmuel.
So that's the same as שמואל. Shmuel. So if you're agreeing... So
אמר רבינא Amar Ravina לא lo מר כתובתה מאחר מנה. mar k'suvosa
me'acher manah.
No, what he's saying is is that if the husband were to
die now before she got to the husband's house but she's being
transported by the husband's messengers then when she came to get married
a second time it would be considered a second marriage. She would
be considered to be an אלמנה מן הנישואין. almana min hanissu'in. An
אלמנה מן האירוסין almana min ha'erusin since it's not a context of
having sex is still considered a בתולה besula and still gets 200.
An אלמנה מן הנישואין almana min hanissu'in because it's considered a context
of sex gets only 100. So even though here she's just being
transported by the שלוחים shluchim and she's not yet in the husband's
house and able to yet have sex, right,
conceptually she's a נשואה nissu'ah that even were the husband to die
she would be considered a בעולה be'ula even though of course that's
not physically possible and therefore she would only get 100 if she
got remarried.
So we have these 100 from this dead husband? What?
Yes, sure, sure. She'll get 200 even before נישואין nissu'in even at
אירוסין. erusin. Right. Okay, and so here,
so here we're saying that she'd be considered a נשואה. nissu'ah. Okay,
for the purposes of of next כתובה k'suva purposes. Okay.
So now we have she gets he'd inherit her she'd be a
נשואה nissu'ah for next כתובה. k'suva. I mean what are they saying?
What about all the other things? Just these things? It sounds like
they're saying that actually although the משנה Mishnah says she's considered 100
percent in the husband's control and רב Rav just said well we'll
exclude one thing תרומה terumah now it looks like we're going to
the opposite extreme and saying the משנה Mishnah doesn't mean it. She's
really just for one or two things in the husband's control. She's
really not a נשואה nissu'ah until this stage. Yes Charlie.
They skipped from שמואל Shmuel to רבינא, Ravina, that's about 200 years
apart.
Yeah, that's a good point.
Alright, but it is a sweeping thing of עולם היא olam hi
that we're saying. I understand.
The גמרא Gemara might interpret these earlier statements to be לאו דווקא
lav davka and to really mean for most things she is except
for תרומה. terumah. Let's take a look. רבי יוחנן ורבי חנינה דאמרי
תרוייהו, Rabbi Yochanan veRabbi Chanina d'amri tarvaihu, רבי יוחנן ורבי חנינה Rabbi
Yochanan veRabbi Chanina both say מסירתה לכל אף לתרומה. mesirasah lekhol af
leterumah.
That's sort of like the רב אסי Rav Asi position. Take the
משנה Mishnah 100 percent okay and even for תרומה. terumah. אף לתרומה.
Af leterumah. מיתיבי. Meisvei. Now here's a תוספתא Tosefta that sounds very
much like רב's Rav position maybe like שמואל's Shmuel also. Let's take
a look. הלכה עם שלוחי הבעל שהלכו שלוחי אבי עם
שלוחי הבעל Halacha im shluchei habaal shehalchu shluchei avi im shluchei habaal
או שהייתה לו חצר בדרך ונכנסה עמו ללין. o shehayesa lo chatzer
baderech venichnesa imo lalin.
Now let's say there they are they're going on the way okay
and she enters in to her own חצר chatzer to
and her own she's got it's her own house somewhere you know
somewhere
midway and they go there to sleep. They're not having sex they
just go there to sleep.
To בעל's baal here you know?
And the בעל baal is there in that case. Right. Okay,
but it's not the בעל's baal house essentially it's her house. Okay,
and they're... that's her father's house either.
That's true. אף על פי שכתובתה בבית בעלה Af al pi shekesuvosah
beveise baalah
even though the dowry maybe has been entrusted to the husband already
at this stage the physical property that is the כתובה k'suva has
been transferred over to the husband's house. Nevertheless she's not yet a
נשואה. nissu'ah. מתה אביה יורשה Meisa aviha yorshah
if she dies her father inherits the dowry. Okay, so she's not
yet a נשואה nissu'ah because it doesn't matter where the physical property
of the dowry is that only becomes the husband's at the time
of נישואין nissu'in and since the father is still with her she's
not a נשואה. nissu'ah. Now מסר האב לשלוחי הבעל masar ha'av lishluchei
habaal
the father handed her over to the husband's messengers או שמסרו שלוחי
אב לשלוחי הבעל o shemasru shluchei av lishluchei habaal or the father's
messengers handed her off או שהייתה o shehayesa or forget the whole
messenger thing שהייתה לו חצר בדרך shehayesa lo chatzer baderech לא lo
he had he had a courtyard on the way the בעל baal
ונכנסה עמו לשם נישואין venichnesa imo leshum nissu'in
and they went there to say let's start let's start you know
go there and make house now they didn't necessarily have sex but
they just went there as a married couple okay אף על פי
שכתובתה בבית אביה Af al pi shekesuvosah beveise aviha then the opposite
is true even if the property for her כתובה k'suva is in
her father's house מתה בעלה יורשה meisa baalah yorshah she's a נשואה
nissu'ah and the husband will inherit her. Okay, so basically what you
have here in addition to the new interesting thing about the חצר
chatzer is that the whole focus is when is she when she's
considered a נשואה nissu'ah her husband inherits her. So the whole focus
is the כתובה k'suva and it doesn't matter where physically the כתובה
k'suva property is the dowry property is it's a question about is
she a נשואה nissu'ah and that determines if the husband inherits her.
So this is like שמואל Shmuel it emphasizes that at this moment
the husband inherits. Then it goes on במה דברים אמורים לירושתה bameh
devarim amurim liyerushasah
when is that true that we consider her a נשואה nissu'ah for
in order for him to inherit her אבל לירושתה aval liyerushasah
where am I אבל לתרומה aval leterumah but when it comes to
תרומה terumah אין אשה אוכלת בתרומה עד שתיכנס לחופה. ein ishah ocheles
biterumah ad shetikanes lachuppah. She has to actually go to the חופה
chuppah which would actually mean either literally or symbolically the husband's house.
Now here you understand And right? Why basically שמואל—forget Shmuel this נשואה—שמואל
says ירושה, yerusha, and רב Rav says תרומה. trumah. They both agree
that this is a middle stage, but they're reflecting the ברייתא, baraita,
the תוספתא. tosefta. The תוספתא tosefta says in this middle stage she's
entitled to—he's entitled to inherit her. Well that's what the ברייתא baraita
says. רב Rav says in this middle stage he gets everything except
תרומה. trumah. That's the end of the ברייתא, baraita, that תרומה—she trumah
gets it whatever, whatever—she doesn't get any תרומה. trumah. That's the end
of the ברייתא, baraita, that until she's fully married she doesn't get
תרומה. trumah. It doesn't tell you what's true about everything in the
middle, right? But basically רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel are both reflecting
in their statements the two statements of the ברייתא, baraita, that at
this stage she definitely—he definitely gets ירושה, yerusha, and תרומה trumah eating
doesn't begin until they actually start living together. It doesn't tell you
anything about the middle, but it does tell you minimum that definitely
ירושה yerusha takes place, תרומה trumah does not take place. Okay, so
that reflects the idea that although the משנה Mishnah makes it sound
like it's 100%, the ברייתא baraita makes it clear that it's some
middle stage. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay.
תיובתא דכולהו תיובתא. Tyufta dekulu tyufta. This is a contradiction of everybody.
Now what does everybody mean? רש"י Rashi says everybody who argues on
שמואל. Shmuel You could have said, תוספות Tosafot says everybody who really,
who argues on רב Rav also, because it says the other half
says she doesn't yet eat תרומה. trumah. Basically it's a contradiction to
anybody who would say that it's 100%. From the ברייתא baraita it's
clear it's not 100% before she starts living with the husband. Okay,
what's clearly true is that the husband inherits her. What's clearly not
yet true is that she eats תרומה. trumah. What about the middle
things—not clear. Now by the way we should point out, you could
come up with a lot of reasons why should we say inherit
her more than anything else, but the degree that this is an
idea of רשות reshut and control and almost that she's being seen
of as a little bit like property, so you understand that if
she is under in his control, then the dowry that she's bringing
in is also physically under his control. If she's transferring as it
were to his ownership, his property, then that's true also about the
property that she's bringing in. So you understand that the most obvious
thing that transfers at this stage is the dowry and the ירושה,
yerusha, whereas תרומה trumah at the other end as we said is—might
be about them actually physically, you know, having had sex and being
together physically as husband and wife, and that's the one thing that
wouldn't. What about the middle things? What about everything else that's not
תרומה trumah and not ירושה? yerusha? That's not clear. Now what we're
also pointing towards, which we're going to get to later is, you
know, which גמרא Gemara is not explicit about but it's going to
actually raise in a minute—here the emphasis is רשות, reshut, רשות, reshut,
רשות, reshut, רשות, reshut, and it's about mostly about the big נפקא
מינא nafka mina is inheriting and is about monetary issues, property. Okay,
but the other thing when we talked about תרומה, trumah, we talked
about sex. And therefore we're going to get to that in a
minute as well. For example, the fact that you consider a woman
who's a נשואה nissuah to be a בעולה, beulah, and she doesn't
get her כתובה ketubah of 200, next time she'll only get a
כתובה ketubah of 100, is the basic assumption that after נישואין nissuin
they're having sex. Right, and if you think about what we do
right now in terms of חופה, chuppah, we actually do two things.
We do the חופה, chuppah, which represents the home, right, and if
you would, property, being in the one person's domain. And then what
do we do after the
חופה? chuppah? יחוד yichud room, which is about them being intimate and
having sex. So those are really the two implicit things that happened
classically: a woman goes to the husband's house, she's in his domain,
and they're private and intimate and can begin a sexual life. So
what happens if you have one without the other? Going to the
שלוחי הבעל shluchei habaal is sort of the domain and the control
and the property without yet the ability to be having sex, which
happens at the next stage. Okay, you could imagine let's say they
had a יחוד yichud room which he didn't own. That could be
the ability to be having sex and being intimate without having the
sense of the property. So how much is נישואין nissuin in this
חופה—the chuppah idea of his רשות, reshut, the idea of them having
privacy and being able to be intimate and have sex? Or is
it the combination of the two? And that's really the issue that
is debated in the ראשונים Rishonim and really is reflected in our
גמרא Gemara here. This middle stage we're talking about is all about
the essences of רשות, reshut, which might be why it's only partial.
You certainly don't have the תרומה trumah yet, which is about them
being—and you certainly do have the ירושה, yerusha, which is about the
sense of property and ownership. And we're about to transition now to
look at discussions which more emphasize the model of them actually having
had sex. So these are the two models, and it might be
required the combination of the two.
Yes, I was going to—I want—I hope this is the same thing
as you've been explaining. It seems at this point in the סוגיא
sugya that they seem to distinguish and to clarify the difference between
רשות, reshut, like he's got a place in the חצר chatzer and
she goes in with him—that's רשות—but reshut she can't eat תרומה trumah
because there's not חופה. chuppah. So רשות reshut and חופה chuppah are
two different things. It's in the language here.
Yes, right. Exactly. Exactly. So what it means by חופה chuppah is
not clear. What's חופה chuppah adding that's not this issue about the
רשות? reshut? It could just mean physically his own domain as opposed
to being transported to his domain, which is the issue about the
שלוחים. shluchim.
Two questions: do we also sort of parallel this to— Just question,
are we also sort of parallel this to an עבד עברי eved
Ivri can't eat at a סעודת תרומה? se'udat terumah? Let's say he
can't eat until he sees them work, or let's say? No.
No, because it's not as much a question of
intimacy, but you said something about, I want to make sure that
I understood this correctly, about him owning it? So let's say the
bride pays for the wedding, so they're not considered married because they
didn't, he didn't own the יחוד yichud room? Like, I miss something?
No, I mean, how much, I mean, whatever. I tell the grooms
to make sure that they've rented the יחוד yichud room for themselves
personally, but bottom line is they're going to go home and how
much is it, that's a question about what satisfies symbolically, you know,
as opposed to it might be in principle you need it to
be his רשות, reshut, but you don't actually need him to own
it. It might be that what we have is more symbolic. No,
but it might be it's symbolic. I'm not getting into now the
exact technical requirements. I'm talking about the model. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, it says like this. הא גופא קשיא. Ha gufa kashya.
Okay,
this itself is internal contradiction in terms of this issue about going
into the yard and going into the חצר, chatzer, which by the
way is also that emphasis of רשות, reshut, right? That emphasis of
whose domain is it? הא גופא קשיא. Ha gufa kashya. מר שנכנסה
עמו ללין, Mar shenichnesa imo lalin, you went to sleep, טעמא דללין,
ta'ama de'lalin, הא סתמא לשם נישואין. ha stama leshem nisuin. If it
wasn't explicitly labeled as we're just going in there to sleep, then
you would have interpreted it as not that we don't here mean
that they're having sex, which would just mean you would have interpreted
the context as we're going there to live as a married couple,
and then it would have been a חופה. chuppah. אימא סיפא, Eima
seifa, look at the end. נכנסה עמו לשם נישואין, Nichnesa imo leshem
nisuin, when it talks about going into his חצר, chatzer, נכנסה עמו
לשם נישואין, nichnesa imo leshem nisuin,
going in for the purpose of נישואין, nisuin, הא סתמא ללין, ha
stama lalin, which means that without explicitly being labeled, we'll assume they're
just sleeping there and it doesn't have the context of נישואין. nisuin.
אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, סתמי סתמי קתני. stami stami katani.
No,
it's talking about what is the assumed context based on the, you
know, based on the specifics. סתם חצר דידה, Stam chatzer didah,
if it's her courtyard, ללין, lalin, then without being labeled as anything
else, we'll assume that it just means that they're sleeping there that
night, but it doesn't mean that we should interpret it as like
a marital context. סתם חצר דידיה, Stam chatzer didey, his courtyard,
לנישואין, lenisuin, we'll assume it as a marital and again for the
obvious reason that the standard beginning of the married house is the
bride moving into the groom's house. And therefore, even if they're not
yet at his house, they're just in his courtyard and they're just
sleeping over and they haven't labeled it as anything, the context will
define it as, oh, now they're beginning as a married couple. Where
if it's her courtyard, the context will be defined as other way.
By the way, it's pretty interesting because in the תורה, Torah, על
כן יעזב איש את אביו ואת אמו ודבק באשתו, al ken ya'azov
ish et aviv ve'et imo vedavak be'ishto, a man leaving his parents,
but of course we basically has always assumed that the bride is
moving into the groom's house. Okay, so here it all is about
whose domain and the שלוחים shluchim are bringing to the husband or
the courtyard is husband's domain. Now, it's not just physically entering into
somebody's yard, it's in the context of נישואין. nisuin. But we don't
yet have here the idea of sex, it's all about domain. And
again, when it's in the שלוחים, shluchim, not even yet physically in
his domain, but somewhat under his control, that might be an interesting
middle state. Now we're going to get to the other model, which
is the model of sex. Let's take a look. תנא, Tana, מסרה
לשלוחי הבעל וזינתה, masra lishluchei haba'al vezinta, הרי זו בחנק. harei zu
bechenek. Once she's given over to the husband's messengers and now she
were to commit adultery, it would no longer be the נערה מאורסה,
na'arah me'orasah, it would actually now be the case of getting execution
by strangulation, not by stone. Okay, now where do we get this
from? מנא הני מילי? Mena hanei milei? אמר רב אמי בר חמא,
Amar Rav Ami Bar Chama, אמר קרא, amar krah, the verse says,
לזנות בית אביה, liznot beit aviha, to fornicate in her father's house.
This is by the נערה מאורסה. na'arah me'orasah. פרט לשנמסרה לשלוחי הבעל,
Prat leshenimsara lishluchei haba'al, once she's out of the father's house, it's
no longer בית אביה. beit aviha. Okay, so that doesn't yet say
what constitutes נישואין, nisuin, that in a more of a way just
says she's no longer in בית אביה. beit aviha. So the גמרא
Gemara says, ואימא פרט שנכנסה לחופה ולא נבעלה, ve'eima prat shenichnesa lechuppah
velo niv'ala, maybe I should wait until she actually has entered into
the חופה. chuppah. Admittedly, although she might still be a virgin, because
then I don't need any חידוש, chiddush, the תורה Torah says she's
a virgin, but maybe the transition state for this נערה מאורסה na'arah
me'orasah is not leaving the father's house but entering into the husband's
domain. And again, pointing out that their שלוחים shluchim state is not
yet what we would call חופה. chuppah. The שלוחים shluchim state is
being brought to his domain, but not yet physically in his domain.
So maybe that's what I would need? So אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
אמר לי אמי, amar li Ami, so אמי Ami told me, חופה
בהדיא כתיבא. chuppah behedya ketiva. No, חופה chuppah we could have learned
from the, we could have already learned before you get to בית
אביה. beit aviha. How do you know this? כי יהיה נערה בתולה
מאורסה לאיש, Ki yihiyeh na'arah betulah me'orasah le'ish, if there is a
virgin lass betrothed to a man, נערה, na'arah, virgin,
you know, a young woman, ולא בוגרת, velo bogeret, not past puberty.
בתולה, betulah, virgin, ולא בעולה, velo be'ulah, not having had sex. מאורסה,
me'orasah,
she is
betrothed, ולא נשואה, velo nesu'ah, and she's not at the stage of
being a נשואה. nissuah מאי נשואה? Mai nesu'ah? Now, what would it
mean to call her a, to be a נשואה? nesu'ah. That's not
already covered in the verse. אילימא נשואה ממש, Ilima nesuah mamash, if
you say a literal נשואה, nesu'ah? she's fully married, היינו בעולה, hainu
b'ulah, you've already excluded it because you said she have to be
a virgin. ולא בעולה v'lo b'ulah and not a woman who's had
sex. אלא, Ela, so by excluding a נשואה, nesuah, you're saying שנכנסה
לחופה ולא נבעלה. shenichnesah l'chuppah v'lo niv'alah. She's gone to the חופה,
chuppah, which again presumably means like the husband's house, okay, but hasn't
yet had sex. So she's not excluded by the word virgin, but
she is excluded by the word מאורסה. me'orasah. Once she's in a
state of נשואה nesuah, even if she's still a virgin, she's out
of the category of נערה מאורסה. naarah me'orasah. That state is חופה.
chuppah. Okay, now, but, and then you have that. And then the
third פסוק pasuk says בית אביה, beis aviah,
that's even at an earlier stage, that's even once she left the
father's house. So you understand meaning what we have here is, right,
the פסוקים psukim say, right,
לזנות בית אביה, liznos beis aviah, in this stage, right, here's the
state of בית אביה. beis aviah. Okay, and then you have שלוחים,
shluchim, and then you have חופה, chuppah, and then you have sex.
Right, and then you have ביאה. biah. Okay, right. So the פסוק
pasuk says, right, if she's נערה, naarah, she's a בתולה, besulah, so
she's a בתולה, besulah, then she's, then it means there hasn't been
ביאה biah yet. Okay, but she's a, anyway, whatever, fine, fine, fine.
She's a מאורסה me'orasah shows
that she's not a נשואה. nesuah Okay, so מאורסה me'orasah means not
a נשואה, nesuah. right, because that, which would mean חופה. chuppah. But
then it's לזנות בית אביה, liznos beis aviah,
לזנות בית אביה liznos beis aviah means as opposed to here, when
she's given over to the שלוחים. shluchim. Okay, then she's, so as
soon as she's given over to the שלוחים, shluchim, she doesn't have
the category of נערה מאורסה. naarah me'orasah. But what that means is,
this is such a great little discussion in these three lines because
it talks to you about there being three stages. Stage one is
she leaves the father's control in the hands of the שלוחים. shluchim.
Not yet in the husband's house, not yet intimacy, but going towards
the husband's house, in the husband's control, that's leaving בית אביה. beis
aviah. That's already enough for נערה מאורסה, naarah me'orasah, she's not נערה
מאורסה, naarah me'orasah, and that's this interesting middle stage. ירושה Yerushah yes,
תרומה terumah no, other things who knows. Then she has the חופה.
chuppah. She's considered classic נשואה. nesuah, Then she actually has sex. Three
stages. So the quest, and what's interesting from the question of the
models is, that at the end it says about נשואה ממש, nesuah
mamash, remember the phrase the גמרא Gemara used? When it says נשואה
ממש, nesuah mamash, היינו בעולה, hainu b'ulah, you know, היינו בעולה. hainu
b'ulah. So that basic, you know, so that basically says that the
classic נשואה nesuah. is the woman that has had sex, maybe been
in the husband's house and had sex, right? So that raises then
this question of, so what is the basic model, right? Is this
clear here? This is basically control, this is גמרא Gemara says to
have had sex. Is the basic model of being a נשואה nesuah
in the husband's house with the possibility of sex, and these are
stages leading up to it? Or is the basic model about sex
or is the basic model about being in the husband's house? You
have all of those, you have all of those things that are
going on. Okay, but it said that again, what's interesting is that
it says נשואה ממש nesuah mamash is a woman that's had sex.
חופה Chuppah is quasi-נשואה. nesuah And this really seems to suggest that
the model is more about sex than it is about being in
the husband's control, or at least about some combination,
or at least about some combination of the two. Okay, so now,
so this is the basic idea of the moment of חופה. chuppah.
Now we wrap this up. ואימא היכא דהדרא לבי נשא הדרא למילתא
קמייתא, V'eima heicha d'hadra l'bei nasha hadra l'milsa kmaisa, maybe I would
say, one minute the גמרא Gemara says, what's the story if after
the שלוחי הבעל, shluchei habaal, the husband dies? Maybe then since she
has not yet been in the husband's house, maybe then she actually
goes back to her original state, right, and maybe then she actually
would be considered like I don't know, you know, נערה בתולה naarah
besulah again, and if she was, and if she was מאורסה me'orasah
to another man, maybe her state would reverse, you know, who knows
what happens.
בי נשא bei nasha is a question. It could either mean the
wife's house, the woman's house, which is not her husband's house but
her original house of origin, or it could be some say the
word נשא nasha means the forgotten house. But again, it means her
original father's house, not her newly adopted house. When a woman brings
a property into the father's estate, into the husband's estate, and she's
been independent of her parents for a while, then the classic thing
to write is דהנעלת לה מבי נשא, d'hanalas leh mibei nasha, that
she brought into the husband's estate from the, from the forgotten house,
which basically, you know, means like she's, she's coming like she's independent
of her father. It's a, it's a, yeah, it's not, there's a
lot of possible meanings to it based on context. Anyway, so maybe
I should say that if the husband dies after the שלוחי הבעל,
shluchei habaal, she goes back to her original state and she's ממש
mamash fully considered back to her father's house. So אמר רבא *Amar
Rava*, ההוא כבר פסקה תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל *hahu kvar paska Tana
d'vei Rabbi Yishmael*. No, that we learn from the תנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל *Tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael*. The תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל *Tana d'vei
Rabbi Yishmael*, ונדר אלמנה וגרושה כל אשר אסרה על נפשה יקום עליה
*v'neder almanah u'grushah kol asher asrah al nafshah yakum aleha*. The vow
of a widow or a divorcee, whatever she vows will be established
on her, מה תלמוד לומר *ma talmud lomar*, why do I need
a פסוק *pasuk* to tell me that? והוא מוצאת מכלל אב ומוצאת
מכלל בעל *v'hu motzet miklal av u'motzet miklal baal*. This woman who
is married off and נשואה nesuah. *nessuah* and then her husband died
or divorced her, she's no longer in her father's house, no longer
in her husband's house. I don't need a פסוק *pasuk* to tell
me that there's nobody to annul it, of course there's nobody to
annul it. אלא הרי שמסר אב וכו׳ *Ela harei shemasar av v'chu*,
it's telling me this middle case. הרי שמסר אב לשלוחי הבעל או
שמסרו שלוחי אב לשלוחי הבעל *Harei shemasar av lishluchei habaal o shemasru
shluchei av lishluchei habaal*. She hasn't yet fully entered the father's house,
she's the husband's house, she's just been given over to the messengers.
או שמסרו שלוחי אב לשלוחי הבעל ונתארמלה בדרך או נתגרשה *O shemasru
shluchei av lishluchei habaal v'nitarmalah baderech o nitgarshah* and he died or
divorced her before she even fully entered into his house, היכא נקרי
בה *heicha nikri bah*? בית אביה של זו או בית בעלה של
זו *Beis aviha shel zo o beis baalah shel zo*. So what
what should I label her? Should I say that she was already
in the husband's house or maybe I should say she wasn't fully
in the husband's house and the husband now divorced her, so maybe
she goes back to the father's house and maybe now the father
can annul her vows? אלא לומר לך *Ela lomar lach*, so the
verse is telling you, no, that now she is fully independent. נדר
אלמנה וגרושה *Neder almanah u'grushah*, it doesn't matter when she becomes an
אלמנה *almanah* and גרושה *grushah*, even from this state of being given
over to the שלוחים Shluchim, *shluchim*, she is now fully independent. Okay,
אלא לומר לך כיון שיצאה שעה אחת מרשות אב *ela lomar lach
kivan sheyatzah shaah achas mereshus av*, once she left the father's control,
שוב אינו יכול להפר *shuv eino yachol l'hafer*, he cannot annul. Now
again notice the power of this statement. It doesn't say כיון שנכנסה
לרשות הבעל *kivan shenichnesah l'reshus habaal*. It's כיון שיצאה מרשות האב Ha'av
*kivan sheyatzah mereshus haav*, right? So once you go over to the
שלוחים *shluchim*, right, she's out of the father's control. And if she
were now to become independent because the husband would die or divorce
her, she's a fully independent woman, and she does not go back
to בית אביה *beis aviha*. Okay, so again I love this גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara* because I see everybody else is not as excited as
I am. But it's so great because it deals with this transition
and middle stages, right? You leave one control, you don't necessarily go
to the next yet. She's sent by the שלוחים *shluchim*, she's out
of the father's control, but she's not yet fully into the husband's.
And then she goes under the חופה Chuppah *chuppah* and maybe she's
symbolically in the husband's רשות Reshus *reshus* or in his property, but
they're not yet having sex. And then they have sex and that's
the final stage. So what exactly is the different statuses that obtain
by each? So what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying is once
she left בית אביה *beis aviha*, then even if the husband divorced
her and even if she's not a hundred percent in his control,
she's never going back to בית אביה *beis aviha*. She remains independent.
And now if the husband were to die she would continue what?
Yeah, but from there we learn symbolically for everything she remains independent,
okay? So we have the idea that as soon as it's given
over she leaves בית אביה *beis aviha*, maybe not yet in his
control for תרומה *terumah*, for other purposes, certainly for some issues under
the husband's control like for ירושה *yerusha* issues and so on. And
then you have חופה Chuppah *chuppah*, which we don't exactly know how
חופה Chuppah? *chuppah* is defined. Let's say it means his property, but
does it mean his property or does it mean his property and
they can be private and intimate and have sex? And it's the
possibility of having sex. And then we have what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* calls בעולה ממש *beulah mamash* is when they're actually living together
and having sex. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. אמר
רב פפא אף אנן נמי תנינא *Amar Rav Papa af anan
nami tanina*. We taught similarly to this idea that the state changes
as soon as it's given over to the שלוחים *shluchim*. הבא על
נערה Na'arah, המאורסה אינו חייב עד שתהא נערה Na'arah. בתולה מאורסה והיא
בבית אביה *Haba al naarah hameorasah eino chayav ad shetehei naarah besulah
meorasah v'hi b'veis aviha*. So the סקילה *sekilah* is only all that
whole פרשה *parsha* is when she is נערה *naarah*, she's betrothed, and
still in the father's house. So בשלמא נערה *bishlama naarah*, I get
the idea of נערה *naarah* ולא בוגרת Bogeres? *v'lo bogeres*, not past
puberty. בתולה ולא בעולה *Besulah v'lo beulah*, virgin not having had sex.
מאורסה ולא נשואה *Meorasah v'lo nessuah*. Okay, and מאורסה *meorasah* means not
having נשואין *nessuin*, not having let's say חופה *chuppah*. But בבית אביה
למעוטי מאי *b'veis aviha l'mauti mai*, what does בבית אביה *b'veis aviha*
come to exclude? מאי לאו למעוטי מסר אב לשלוחי הבעל *Mai lav
l'mauti masar av lishluchei habaal*? This case where she's no longer in
בית אביה *beis aviha* even if there's not yet been חופה *chuppah*,
even in this middle stage. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק אף אנן
נמי תנינא *Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak af anan nami tanina*. הבא
על אשת איש כיון שנכנסה לרשות הבעל לנשואין *Haba al eshes ish
kivan shenichnesah l'reshus habaal l'nessuin*. Somebody has sex with a married woman
once she's been in the husband's control for נשואין *nessuin* purposes. אף
על פי שלא נבעלה *Af al pi shelo nivalah*, even though she
hasn't had sex. הבא עליה הרי זה בחנק *Haba alei harei zeh
b'chenek*. She gets strangled as opposed to stoning. נכנסה לרשות הבעל בעלמא
*Nichnesah l'reshus habaal b'alma*, just going into the husband's רשות Reshus. *reshus*,
not yet fully חופה *chuppah*, not yet fully sex, just entering, beginning
to enter into his רשות Reshus *reshus* once given over to the
שלוחים *shluchim*. שמע מינה *Shma mina*, that you hear from it. So
when she leaves בית אביה *beis aviha* and she's in the שלוחים
*shluchim*, she's no longer נערה המאורסה *naarah hameorasah*, that requires בית אביה
*beis aviha*. The husband now inherits her. What about all the other
statuses of נשואין *nessuin*? Not clear. But תרומה *terumah* certainly won't begin
until they've actually begun to live together and been in the husband's
house. Okay, and what is remains as the big debate in the
ראשונים *Rishonim* is, bottom line, what are we telling you? What is
חופה *chuppah* in essence? Is חופה *chuppah* in essence an idea of
רשות Reshus *reshus* or is חופה *chuppah* in essence an idea of...
of privacy, intimacy, having sex, or maybe it is both? So maybe
if you have our חופה, and then you have a ייחוד Yichud
room that you don't own, you don't have חופה at all because
you have our חופה is maybe רשות Reshus? without the possibility of
sex, right? And the ייחוד Yichud room is a possibility of sex
without it being his רשות. Now, clearly in our discussion, his assumption
of his control dominated. So whether it's his שלוחים, whether it's his
חצר, Chatzer, that idea
of his control dominated. So the idea of the possibility of sex
without an idea of it being רשות is very much not in—or
there's no indication for that. But the idea that the ideal model
is both his רשות and the intimacy possibility, that I would say
is definitely what is strongly suggested here. Yes, Charlie.
Quick question. They've not made distinctions here for the most part between
a קטנה, Ketannah, נערה, and בוגרת?
Bogeres Yeah, that's what I said at the beginning. We are assuming
קטנה Ketannah or נערה. The חז"ל Chazal open up this big space
called בוגרת Bogeres, from the time she's twelve and a half that
she's completely independent and no longer—she can live a life independent of
any man's control, okay? But that's not in the תורה. Torah. תורה
Torah might have imagined that even as a בוגרת, Bogeres the father
controls her, or it might have imagined that a woman would never
get to that old age of being a בוגרת Bogeres without being
married off. But it's the רבנים Rabbanim that open up that big
space, okay? It's not clear in the תורה, Torah, and this discussion
here parallels those פסוקים Pesukim in the תורה, Torah, does not imagine
a space between father's house and husband's house.
Yes. Second question, one other הלכה Halachah regarding married women that hasn't
been mentioned here is the obligation to cover hair.
When does that—That's coming, don't worry. Okay, moving on.
Do you know it's not conventional classic ספרדי Sephardi practice to have
a separate ייחוד Yichud room?
Right, well, the general—the question is about whether we at all need
a ritual of נישואין Nissuin to take place at the wedding and
whether the whole idea that we need עדים Edim for it is
big questionable. It might just be the reality of them starting to
live together. So they go home that night, you know, and that's
the end of the story. And if you—know, all right. So let's
take a look at the משנה. Mishnah.
האב—by the way, I guess I should also mention here the other
relevant question in addition to like, do you tell the חתן—there's Chasan
a lot of questions. Do you tell the חתן Chasan to rent
the ייחוד Yichud room? Is it important, as I've been mentioning, that
he also own it, that it's an idea of his רשות?
There's a question about do you need witnesses or is it—it's not
necessarily a formal—to witness the ייחוד, Yichud, to witness the חופה? It's
not necessarily a formal act, it might just be a reality of
them beginning to live together. And the third question is what do
you do about a חופת נידה? Chuppas Niddah? Maybe חופת נידה Chuppas
Niddah doesn't work because if it's about them having the ability to
be having sex, then that's not possible with a חופת נידה. Chuppas
Niddah. So there's all those questions emerge from the implicit issues that
are going on in the discussion we just read. Let's take a
look now. האב אינו חייב במזונות בתו. Ha'av eino chayav bimzonos bito.
We've already implicitly said it, now we're explicitly saying it. A father
is not obligated to feed his daughters. It's really not obligated to
feed his sons either, but we're going to talk about why we're
mentioning his daughters. זה מדרש דרש רבי אלעזר בן עזריה לפני חכמים
בכרם ביבנה. Ze midrash darash Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah lifnei Chachamim be-Kerem
be-Yavneh.
This מדרש—you Midrash know, expounded רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben
Azaryah in front of the sages in the Kerem be-Yavneh, where the,
you know, rabbis sort of the rabbinic academy was after the חורבן
הבית. Churban ha-Bayis. Right, we're coming up to פסח, Pesach, right? אמר
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה הרי אני כבן שבעים שנה, Amar Rabbi Elazar
ben Azaryah harei ani ke-ven shivim shanah, right, that famous מדרש Midrash
that he grow—grew old or looked old on the day he was
appointed as the head of the—of the—of the
ישיבה. Yeshivah. So this was the day that he was appointed as
the—as the אב בית דין. Av Beis Din. זה מדרש דרש. Ze
midrash darash. הבנים יירשו
והבנות ייזונו. Ha-banim yirshu ve-ha-banos yizonu.
So the כתובה Kesubah says, one of the lines of the כתובה,
Kesubah, not our כתובה, Kesubah, but a classic line of the כתובה
Kesubah in time of חז"ל, Chazal, and an implicit condition whether it's
written or not, is that the father basically says two things. Number
one, you might remember this: I will continue to—if I die and
the—our daughters are not yet married off, the daughters will continue to
be supported by the estate because that's again, you know, the girls
have to be supported by the father or protected by the fathers.
The daughters will continue to be supported by the estate until they
become a בוגרת or until they go ahead and get married. Okay,
so that's one thing he ad—promises to his wife in the כתובה,
Kesubah, that the daughters who don't inherit will be protected and supported
by the estate until they get married. The other thing he says
to his wife is: your sons, the sons that we have together,
they'll inherit your portion of the כתובה. Kesubah. Now, what are you
talking about? Why do you have to say that? The sons inherit
anyway. Because he might have multiple wives. So here, wife number one
brings in a million dollars of dowry. Wife number two brings in
a thousand dollars
of dowry. What's going to happen? Both his wives predecease him, then
he dies. All the kids will equally divide the property including the
million dollars that wife number one brought in. Wife number one ain't
so happy about that, that the kids from another marriage are going
to get her dowry. So basically what he says is the money
you've brought in in the dowry, that will be computed separately from
the major—from the whole estate. The whole estate is going to be
divided equally amongst all of my sons, but your—your dowry money will
go only to your sons. sons, only the sons we have together.
And then he says that to the other wife as well. Okay
so that clear? The dowry, that money brought in gets segregated off
and goes only to the woman's sons or their joint sons, not
to all of the sons. Okay so those are the two תנאי
כתובה. tnei ketuvah. So number one is he's promising to support the
daughters. And number two is he is saying that the sons will
inherit him the money of the dowry. So this is the מדרש
midrash that, you know, it's funny, it's like a מדרש midrash on
a secular document, you know, or not on scripture. But this is
the מדרש midrash that רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya
did.
He's going to make like a גזירה שווה. gezeirah shavah. הבנים יירשו
והבנות ייזונו. Habbanim yirshu vehabbanot yizzonu. מה הבנים אינם יורשים אלא לאחר
מיתת האב, Mah habbanim einam yorshim ella le'achar mitat ha'av, the
same way the כתובה ketubah entitles the sons to inherit their mother's
dowry only after the father dies, אף הבנות אינן ניזונות אלא לאחר
מיתת אביהן. af habbanot einan nizzonot ella le'achar mitat avihen. So the
daughters are only legally entitled to be supported by the estate after
the father dies. While the father's alive, he has no legal obligation
to support the daughters. So there are two interesting things. One is
we're going to see this coming up that there actually was—it all
goes all the way back to בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית
שמאי—this Beit Shammai idea of doing a דרש drash on the language
of the כתובה. ketubah. Like sometimes you find this amongst ישיבה בחורים.
yeshiva bachurim. They've been learning too long in ישיבה yeshiva and then
they'll start like reading the newspaper and they'll start making דיוקים. diyukim.
The fact that it says this meant that whatever. So actually those
types of דרשות drashot and דיוקים diyukim get done on the language
of the כתובה, ketubah, which shows that it had just been so
like treated as so like ancient, you know, that it had that
power of the language of the כתובה. ketubah. Number one. Number two
is that you also see a reasonable reason why you had to
emphasize that there's no legal obligation to support the daughters. Because even
though there's no legal obligation to support any of the kids, you
would have said, okay, but the boys can go
ahead and fend for themselves, let them apprentice themselves to somebody. Daughters
you want to keep at home and protect them from the larger
world, and therefore you might think that the daughters, maybe there is
more of a legal obligation to support them even as kids. And
you say, look, and after I die, the daughters are going to
be protected and supported by my estate, so maybe I... there's a
legal obligation that they be protected and supported even while the guy's
alive. It says, no, the same way the sons will only inherit
after you die, the daughters' legal right to be protected and supported
is only after the guy dies. While he's alive, he actually has
no legal right to do so.
So what's the definition of protect and support while he's alive? Nothing.
So you're not protecting and supporting?
You are, but you're not legally bound to. If you're doing it,
you're doing it because you're a good guy and you don't want
to be shamed in society, but you're not legally bound.
מזונות mezonot or מזונון mezonon
until they're בגרות.
bagrut. Until they're בגרות. bagrut. Okay so let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara במזונות בתו הוא דאינו חייב. Bimzonot bitto hu de'eino
chayav. Now the גמרא Gemara talk about doing a little דרש, drash,
so the גמרא Gemara does its own דרש drash on this משנה.
Mishnah. Okay, he's not obligated to support his daughters, so it assumes,
as opposed to the way I just read it, which is the
way the גמרא Gemara? is going to conclude, הא במזונות בנו חייב.
ha bimzonot beno chayav. It sounds like he is supported to feed
his son. בתו נמי חובה הוא דליכא. bitto nami chovah hu deleika.
And also we'll make the other inference: he has no legal obligation
to support his daughters, הא מצווה איכא. ha mitzvah ika. It sounds
like though he has a מצווה mitzvah to support his daughters. So
מאן מתניתין? man matnitin? Who's our משנה? Mishnah? That says... that implies
the way we're choosing to read it, that there's an obligation for
the sons and there's a מצווה mitzvah for the daughters. So מאן
מתניתין? man matnitin? לא רבי מאיר ולא רבי יהודה ולא רבי יוחנן
בן ברוקא. lo Rabbi Meir velo Rabbi Yehudah velo Rabbi Yochanan ben
Beroka. None of these three תנאים. Tannaim. דתניא, detanya, taught a ברייתא.
braita. מצווה לזון את הבנות קל וחומר לבנים. Mitzvah lazon et habbanot
kal vachomer labbanim. There's a מצווה, mitzvah, לא
חובה, lo chovah, not a חובה. chovah. So meaning there's like a
moral religious obligation but not a legal obligation to feed the daughters
and certainly the sons. Why certainly the sons? דעסקי בתורה, de'askei baTorah,
because sons learn תורה, Torah, so all the more that they deserve
support. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. That's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says. Now, pointed out in the side—and you could probably sense yourself
because of the shift to Aramaic—that those words דעסקי בתורה de'askei baTorah
are a gloss. Okay, the גמרא Gemara is glossing and explaining why
does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir think there's more importance to support your
sons? Because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir assumes since they're learning תורה, Torah,
that gives more importance to them. Okay, so that's a gloss that
the גמרא adds in. Okay so that's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. But
at the end of the day, he says there's a מצווה mitzvah
to support both, an obligation to support neither. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi
Yehudah omer, now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says the same, but he
comes to it from a different direction. רבי יהודה אומר מצווה לזון
את הבנים וקל וחומר לבנות. Rabbi Yehudah omer mitzvah lazon et habbanim
vekal vachomer labbanot. It's a מצווה mitzvah to support
the sons, certainly the daughters. Why is there more of an obligation
to support or more of a מצווה mitzvah to support the daughters?
So again the גמרא glosses in, משום זילותא, mishum ziluta,
because otherwise they'll be degraded, right? The idea that they'll be forced
to go out on the street and beg and, you know, put
themselves out there in the larger society, you want to protect the
daughters more than the sons. So if there's a מצווה mitzvah to
feed the sons, certainly there's a מצווה mitzvah to feed the daughters.
So both of them have a מצווה mitzvah to feed both, just
coming from different directions, but not a חובה chovah to feed either.
Okay. רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר חובה לזון את הבנות לאחר מיתת
אביהן. Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka omer chovah lazon et habbanot le'achar mitat
avihen.
Yes,
there's an obligation to feed the daughters after the father dies, אבל
בחיי אביהן, aval bechayei avihen, but
while the father's alive, אלו ואלו אינן ניזונין, elu ve'elu einan nizzonin,
neither of them are fed. Presumably what he's saying is there's not
even a מצוה. mitzvah. Okay? So basically it's not a big debate.
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda both say no
obligation, yes a מצוה. mitzvah. רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rebbi Yochanan ben
Broka says presumably not even a מצוה. mitzvah. So who's our משנה
mishnah says the גמרא? מני מתניתין, mani matnitin, who's our משנה? mishnah?
אי רבי מאיר, ei Rebbi Meir, if it's רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir,
הא אמר בני מצוה. ha amar beni mitzvah. He would say there's
a מצוה mitzvah to the sons, not a חוב, chov, and we
are reading the משנה mishnah that there is an obligation, a legal
obligation to the sons. אי רבי יהודה, ei Rebbi Yehuda, if
it's רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, הא אמר בני נמי מצוה. ha amar
beni nami mitzvah. He says the same
as רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, it's only a מצוה mitzvah for the
sons, but our משנה mishnah suggests the way we've read it until
now that there's a legal obligation to the sons. אי רבי יוחנן
בן ברוקא, ei Rebbi Yochanan ben Broka, if it's רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקא, Rebbi Yochanan ben Broka, אפילו מצוה נמי ליכא. afilu mitzvah nami
leika. There's not even a מצוה mitzvah to the daughters and we're
reading our משנה mishnah that there is a מצוה mitzvah to daughters.
So we read a lot into our משנה, mishnah, so we have
the problem. But the גמרא's going to say none of this is
a problem and the way this is just a nice way to
bring in this debate of תנאים. tannaim. איבעית אימא רבי מאיר, איבעית
אימא רבי יהודה, איבעית אימא רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא. iba'it eima Rebbi
Meir, iba'it eima Rebbi Yehuda, iba'it eima Rebbi Yochanan ben Broka. Now
our משנה mishnah could go like any three of them, any one
of them. Let's just read this and with that we'll end for
today. איבעית אימא רבי מאיר. iba'it eima Rebbi Meir. והכי קאמר, vehachi
ka'amar, it could be like רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
who says there's more of a מצוה mitzvah for the sons but
not an obligation for any. האב אינו חייב במזונות בתו, ha'av eino
chayav bimzonot bito,
the father has no legal obligation to feed the daughter. והוא הדין
לבנו, vehu hadin livno, and no legal obligation to feed the son.
Okay? הא מצוה בבתו איכא, ha mitzvah bevito ika, but there is
a מצוה mitzvah to feed the daughter. וכל שכן לבנים, vechol shekein
levanim, and there's certainly a מצוה mitzvah to feed the sons. So
that's רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. No legal obligation for any, yes a
מצוה mitzvah for both. והאי דקתני בתו, vehai dikatani bito, why does
it only talk about daughters? הא קמשמע לן, ha kamashma lan, it's
teaching you דאפילו בתו חובה הוא דליכא dafilu bito chova hu deleika
to tell you that even the daughter there's only no obligation, הא
מצוה איכא ha mitzvah ika but there is still a מצוה. mitzvah.
So it's to tell you the inference. It is weird. The משנה
mishnah sounds more like רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, which is what we're
about to say. ואיבעית אימא רבי יהודה, ve'iba'it eima Rebbi Yehuda, or
it could be רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. והכי קאמר. vehachi ka'amar. האב
אינו חייב במזונות בתו, ha'av eino chayav bimzonot bito, the father has
no legal obligation to feed his daughter. וכל שכן לבנו vechol shekein
livno and certainly not his son. And that is the way the
משנה mishnah sounds. That's at least the way I presented the משנה
mishnah to you. That I would have thought that you would have
a legal obligation to your daughters because those are the ones you
have to protect more and those are the ones that you do
protect in the כתובה. ketubah. So it's saying no, the father has
no legal obligation to the daughters and certainly not to the sons.
הא מצוה בבנו איכא, ha mitzvah bevino ika, but there is a
מצוה, mitzvah, וכל שכן לבנות vechol shekein labanot that's for sons and
daughters. והאי דקתני בתו, vehai dikatani bito, so why does it say
no obligation for the daughters? קמשמע לן דאפילו בתו חובה ליכא. kamashma
lan dafilu bito chova leika. Even though I would have thought reasonably
that you do have an obligation to your daughter because you know,
she needs to be protected from the larger society and you are
protecting her after you die. No, while you're alive, no legal obligation.
And then the last one, ואיבעית אימא רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא. ve'iba'it
eima Rebbi Yochanan ben Broka. והכי קאמר. vehachi ka'amar. אינו חייב במזונות
בתו, eino chayav bimzonot bito,
you're not obligated to feed your daughter. והוא הדין לבנו, vehu hadin
livno, or your son. והוא הדין דאפילו מצוה נמי ליכא vehu hadin
dafilu mitzvah nami leika and you don't even have a מצוה mitzvah
to feed your sons and daughters. נמי ליכא. nami leika. ואיידי דבנות
אחר מיתת אביהם חובה, ve'aidi debanot achar mitat avihem chova,
so why do we say חובה, chova, why do we say there's
not even a מצוה? mitzvah? Because there is a legal obligation to
feed the daughters after you die. So תניא נמי אינו חייב. tanya
nami eino chayav. So we said while you're alive there's no legal
obligation but in fact while you're alive there's not even a מצוה.
mitzvah. Bottom line is no legal obligation to feed the sons or
the daughters while you're alive. Logically you would have assumed like רבי
יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, I think daughters more, you are protecting the daughters
after you die but while you're alive no legal obligation, presumably at
least there is a מצוה mitzvah and we'll continue to see the
implications of this tomorrow.
Is that unusual that
there's
a
distinction between the language of חובה chova and the language of מצוה?
mitzvah? Yeah.